Hello everyone and welcome back to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎回到EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
My name is Catherine and today we're talking about one of our favorite subjects, food.
我是Catherine，今天我们聊一个我们最喜欢的话题：食物。
That's right and on this occasion we are going to talk about Chinese food, specifically
没错，这次我们要讨论中国菜，特别是
stir fry.
炒菜。
This is a common dish in America and all over the world thanks to the many Cantonese people
这道菜在美国和世界各地都很常见，这要感谢许多来自香港或中国南方的广东人，
who came over from Hong Kong or southern China and brought these delicious foods to our cities.
他们把这种美味带到了我们的城市。
So this is a very popular dish you'll be learning more about.
所以这是一道非常受欢迎的菜，你会了解更多。
So let's jump right in and listen to today's dialogue and don't be worried if you don't
那我们直接开始听今天的对话吧，如果听不懂也别担心，
understand everything.
我们一会儿会回来解释。
We'll be back in a moment.
我们马上回来。
Oh man, I had the best supper last night.
哦天哪，我昨晚吃了一顿超棒的晚餐。
My wife made a stir fry and it was amazing.
我老婆做了炒菜，味道太棒了。
I love stir fry.
我爱炒菜。
Crispy bite-sized vegetables covered in a mixture of soy sauce and oyster sauce, wilted
脆脆的块状蔬菜裹着酱油和蚝油的混合酱汁，还有软塌的绿叶菜
greens and fresh bean sprouts.
和新鲜的豆芽。
Throw in some onion and garlic and ginger.
再加点洋葱、大蒜和姜。
Mmm, it's almost lunch time.
嗯，都快到午饭时间了。
I would die for a plate of stir fry right now.
我现在真想立刻来一盘炒菜。
Well, you can keep the vegetables.
嗯，你可以留着蔬菜。
I'll take the meat.
我吃肉。
The stir fry my wife made was really hearty with chunks of beef and slivers of bell peppers
我老婆做的炒菜很丰盛，有大块的牛肉和青椒丝
and onion.
还有洋葱。
What?
什么？
You call that a stir fry?
你管那叫炒菜？
More meat than vegetables?
肉比蔬菜还多？
It's the worst insult you could throw at a Chinese stir fry.
这是对中国炒菜最大的侮辱。
What a disgrace to the wok she fried it in.
真是对炒锅的亵渎。
What you had is equivalent to a fajita without the wrap.
你吃的那个，跟没有饼皮的铁板烧差不多。
Alright we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So you probably heard a lot of different vegetables and ingredients in this dish.
所以你可能在这道菜里听到了很多不同的蔬菜和配料。
So why don't we take a look at some of those now in Language Takeaway.
那我们不如在“语言小贴士”环节看看其中一些吧。
Language Takeaway.
语言小贴士。
The first two phrases that we have actually, they're not words, they're phrases, are the
我们首先有两个短语，它们不是单词，而是短语，是
names of sauces that are very, very important to Chinese food.
对中国菜非常重要的酱料名称。
The first one is soy sauce.
第一个是酱油。
Okay, soy sauce.
好，酱油。
And it's this black sauce, right?
它是一种黑色的酱汁，对吧？
Very salty.
很咸。
And it's made from?
它是用什么做的？
Soy beans.
大豆。
Soy beans, okay.
大豆，好的。
Soy.
大豆。
So soy is a bean, a vegetable product.
所以大豆是一种豆类，是植物产品。
But soy sauce is a thin, black, salty sauce.
但酱油是一种稀的、黑色的、咸的酱汁。
Okay, and it's very, very common to use it with Chinese dishes especially.
好的，它尤其在中餐里非常常用。
It's very related.
关系很密切。
You usually have sushi with soy sauce.
你通常吃寿司时会配酱油。
Exactly, so Japanese food uses a lot of this too.
没错，所以日本料理也大量使用这个。
Alright and the other sauce that's not very common in our countries is oyster sauce.
好的，另一种在我们国家不太常见的酱汁是蚝油。
Okay, an oyster is an animal that lives in the sea.
好，牡蛎是一种生活在海里的动物。
It lives in a shell and we often eat oysters as a dish.
它住在壳里，我们经常把牡蛎当作一道菜来吃。
But oyster sauce is stinky, thick, dark sauce that is very popular in Southeast Asian, so
但蚝油是一种味道重、浓稠、深色的酱汁，在东南亚菜中很受欢迎，
Vietnamese food as well, and Chinese food.
比如越南菜，还有中餐。
Okay, so it's part of the ingredients of Chinese food.
好的，所以它是中餐配料的一部分。
It's really good.
真的很好吃。
It smells terrible.
闻起来很臭。
It's stinky.
味道很重。
But when you mix it with food and you cook it, it smells, it adds a very, very good flavor.
但当你把它和食物一起烹饪时，它会增添一种非常好的风味。
Absolutely.
绝对没错。
Alright, so that's the sauces.
好的，这就是酱料部分。
Now apart from sauces, we have some vegetables and some of those are bean sprouts.
除了酱料，我们还有一些蔬菜，其中一种是豆芽。
Bean sprouts are very common vegetables, especially in Asian food.
豆芽是非常常见的蔬菜，尤其在亚洲菜中。
So you see a lot of these.
所以你会经常看到它们。
They're usually almost white, almost clear and they're crunchy and they have a little
它们通常几乎是白色的，几乎透明，口感脆脆的，末端还有一点
green part at the end.
绿色。
Right, so they're like little straws with a little green point at the end.
对，它们就像小吸管，末端带点绿色。
So usually those go into your dish at the very end because they cook quickly.
所以通常它们是在最后才放进菜里，因为它们熟得快。
Bean sprouts.
豆芽。
Okay.
好的。
Now if you're cooking stir-fry, what you need is the correct tools and the main tool that
现在，如果你要做炒菜，你需要正确的工具，而主要工具就是
you need is a wok.
炒锅。
That's right.
没错。
So a wok is actually a word that we take from, I think, Cantonese.
所以“wok”这个词，我想是从粤语借来的。
I'm not positive.
我不太确定。
I don't speak Cantonese.
我不会说粤语。
But in English, we normally say frying pan.
但在英语里，我们通常说“frying pan”（煎锅）。
But this is a special Asian frying pan that's very, very large and very thin.
但这是一个特殊的亚洲煎锅，非常大，非常薄。
So foods cook quickly in a wok.
所以食物在炒锅里熟得很快。
Okay.
好的。
It's not like the other pans where it has a big flat part.
它不像其他锅那样有一个大的平底部分。
It's very, very round all over.
它整个非常非常圆。
That's right.
没错。
It's almost like a bowl that sits on your stove and you cook quickly in a wok.
它几乎就像一个放在炉子上的碗，你在炒锅里快速烹饪。
All right.
好的。
So that's a wok.
所以那就是炒锅。
Well, the guy compared his stir-fry to a fajita.
嗯，那家伙把他的炒菜比作法吉塔。
Now fajita, that's not Chinese.
法吉塔，那不是中餐。
And it's not English.
也不是英语。
Okay.
好的。
Well, it is English now.
嗯，现在它已经是英语了。
It's actually the name of a food from Latin America.
它实际上是来自拉丁美洲的一种食物的名字。
So South America and Mexico and Central America, I think more Mexican than anything.
所以是南美洲、墨西哥和中美洲，我觉得更多是墨西哥的。
And it's like slivers of meat, so thin strips of meat and vegetables that you eat in a tortilla
它就像是肉片，薄薄的肉条和蔬菜，你放在玉米饼里吃。
bread.
饼。
Almost.
差不多。
A tortilla is like very thin corn or flour pancake.
玉米饼就像很薄的玉米或面粉薄饼。
Yeah.
是的。
So that's a fajita.
所以那就是法吉塔。
It's kind of, you've probably seen it, a fajita or maybe what's commonly known as well as
它有点像，你可能见过，法吉塔或者通常被称为。
a burrito, which actually is also an American invention.
墨西哥卷饼，实际上也是美国人的发明。
I don't think that exists in Mexico.
我觉得墨西哥没有那个。
No, but they are delicious.
不，但它们很好吃。
I think the word is Tex-Mex, Texas Mexican.
我觉得这个词是德克萨斯-墨西哥风味，德克萨斯墨西哥。
So Tex-Mex.
所以是德克萨斯-墨西哥风味。
All right.
好的。
So that's what we have for you on Language Takeaway.
这就是我们在“语言小贴士”中为你准备的内容。
Why don't we go back to our dialogue, listen to it again, and we'll be back shortly.
我们为什么不回到对话中，再听一遍，我们马上回来。
Oh man, I had the best supper last night.
哦，天哪，我昨晚吃了一顿超棒的晚餐。
My wife made a stir-fry and it was amazing.
我妻子做了炒菜，味道好极了。
I love stir-fry, crispy bite-sized vegetables covered in a mixture of soy sauce and oyster
我喜欢炒菜，脆脆的一口大小的蔬菜，裹着酱油和蚝油的混合物。
sauce, wilted greens and fresh bean sprouts, throw in some onion and garlic and ginger.
软塌的绿叶菜和新鲜的豆芽，再加点洋葱、大蒜和姜。
It's almost lunchtime.
差不多到午饭时间了。
I would die for a plate of stir-fry right now.
我现在真想死也要吃一盘炒菜。
Well, you can keep the vegetables.
嗯，你可以留着蔬菜。
I'll take the meat.
我要吃肉。
The stir-fry my wife made was really hearty with chunks of beef and slivers of bell peppers
我妻子做的炒菜真的很丰盛，有大块的牛肉和薄薄的甜椒片。
and onion.
还有洋葱。
What?
什么？
You call that a stir-fry?
你管那叫炒菜？
More meat than vegetables?
肉比蔬菜还多？
That's the worst insult you could throw at a Chinese stir-fry.
这是对中国炒菜最严重的侮辱。
What a disgrace to the wok she fried it in.
真是对她用来炒菜的炒锅的耻辱。
What you had is equivalent to a fajita without the wrap.
你吃的相当于没有卷饼的法吉塔。
All right, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So now I think we should take a look at some of those phrases that were used in this dialogue
所以现在我觉得我们应该看看这个对话中用到的一些短语。
in Fluency Builder.
在“流利度提升”部分。
Fluency Builder.
流利度提升。
The first phrase we have in Fluency Builder is a phrase that you will hear very often
我们在“流利度提升”中的第一个短语是一个你在看烹饪节目时会经常听到的短语。
when you watch cooking shows.
所以这是一个术语，我们说“扔进去”，扔进去。
So this is a term we say throw in, to throw in.
好的，所以扔进去一些蔬菜或者扔进去一些洋葱和大蒜。
Okay, so throw in some vegetables or throw in some onion and garlic.
那意思就是把它放进锅里，放进罐子里。
And that means to just put it into the pan, put it into the pot.
没错，但它很随意或随便或简单。
That's right, but it's very general or casual or easy.
你就加一些。
You just add some.
如果你想具体点，我们可以说，请加一杯切碎的洋葱。
If you want to be specific, we can say, please add one cup chopped onion.
一杯切碎的洋葱。
One cup of chopped onion.
但在这里，“扔进去”只是意味着随意地加。
But here, throw in just means add casually.
好的，加一些洋葱。
Okay, add some onion.
所以我们扔进去所有这些食材，听起来很好吃，以至于那家伙说，我现在真想死也要吃一盘炒菜。
So we throw in all these ingredients and it sounds so delicious that the guy says, I would
所以那意味着他想要一些炒菜。
die for a plate of stir-fry right about now.
“我死也要”是个好说法。
So that means he wants some stir-fry.
这是一种表达我非常想要某物的方式。
I would die for is a good thing.
这是一种夸张。
It's a way to say I really want something.
并不是你真的会为它去死或者你渴望吃到它。
It's an exaggeration.
这只是夸张，意思是你非常非常想要它。
It's not like you would actually die for it or you are dying to eat it.
我死也要一辆新车。
It's just that it's an exaggeration means that you really, really want it.
我的车旧了，而且从来不好好工作。
I would die for a new car.
好的，所以你真的很想要一辆新车。
My car is old and it never really works.
好的，嗯，那家伙显然不喜欢他说的内容以及他做这道炒菜的方式，他说，真是对她用来炒菜的炒锅的耻辱。
All right, so you really want a new car.
好的，这是一种表达某物不好的方式。
Okay, and well, the guy obviously didn't really like what he was talking about and how he
这很丢脸。
cooked this stir-fry and he said, what a disgrace to the wok she fried it in.
所以我们可以说这个食物是对中餐的耻辱，因为中餐是一种样子，但这甚至看起来不像中餐。
Okay, this is a way to say that something is bad.
所以是耻辱，耻辱。
It's embarrassing.
所以“耻辱”这个词，意思是某物不好。
So we can say that this food is a disgrace to Chinese food because Chinese food is one
或者对别的东西来说很丢脸。
way but this doesn't even look like Chinese food.
所以我们可以说这个食物是对中餐的耻辱，因为中餐是一种样子，但这甚至看起来不像中餐。
So a disgrace, a disgrace.
所以是耻辱，耻辱。
So the word disgrace, it means that something is bad.
所以“耻辱”这个词，意思是某物不好。
Or embarrassing to something else.
或者对别的东西来说很丢脸。
So a parent can say you're a disgrace to this family.
所以家长可以说：“你是这个家的耻辱。”
That means this family has a good reputation but what you did, what you do, these are bad
这意味着这个家本来名声很好，但你做的事、你的行为，都是不好的
things.
事情。
They make us look bad.
它们让我们丢脸。
They are embarrassing.
它们让人难堪。
They are embarrassing to us.
它们让我们难堪。
So it's a very strong phrase.
所以这是一个非常强烈的说法。
This is a disgrace.
这是一种耻辱。
Okay, a disgrace, very good.
好的，耻辱，非常好。
A strong phrase and you can use it if you ever want to talk about someone or something
这是一个强烈的说法，如果你想用这种方式谈论某人或某事，你可以使用它
in this way.
在这种情况下。
But remember, it is pretty strong.
但记住，它相当强烈。
If you say somebody is a disgrace, it's pretty insulting.
如果你说某人是耻辱，那是相当侮辱人的。
It's hurtful.
它很伤人。
Okay, so why don't we listen to our dialogue for one last time and we'll be back.
好的，那我们最后再听一遍对话，然后回来。
Oh man, I had the best supper last night.
哦天哪，我昨晚吃了一顿超棒的晚餐。
My wife made a stir fry and it was amazing.
我妻子做了炒菜，味道好极了。
I love stir fry.
我喜欢炒菜。
Crispy bite-sized vegetables covered in a mixture of soy sauce and oyster sauce.
脆脆的小块蔬菜，裹着酱油和蚝油的混合酱汁。
Wilted greens and fresh bean sprouts.
软塌的青菜和新鲜的豆芽。
Throw in some onion and garlic and ginger.
再加点洋葱、大蒜和姜。
Mmm, it's almost lunch time.
嗯，差不多到午饭时间了。
I would die for a plate of stir fry right now.
我现在真想用命换一盘炒菜。
Well, you can keep the vegetables.
嗯，你可以留着蔬菜。
I'll take the meat.
我要吃肉。
The stir fry my wife made was really hearty with chunks of beef and slivers of bell peppers
我妻子做的炒菜真的很丰盛，有大块牛肉和甜椒丝
and onion.
和洋葱。
Meat?
肉？
You call that a stir fry?
你管那叫炒菜？
More meat than vegetables?
肉比蔬菜多？
That's the worst insult you could throw at a Chinese stir fry.
这是你能对中国炒菜说的最侮辱的话。
What a disgrace to the wok she fried it in.
真是对炒锅的耻辱。
What you had is equivalent to a fajita without the wrap.
你吃的相当于没有卷饼的法士达。
Alright so, talking about Chinese food, there are a lot of American inventions around Chinese
好了，说到中餐，除了墨西哥菜，中餐也有很多美国发明的
food as well, not only Mexican food.
东西。
For example, it's very popular this dish, chopped suey.
比如，有一道菜很流行，叫炒杂碎。
That's right, chopped suey.
没错，炒杂碎。
And I think I read somewhere that chopped suey is actually, might have been a Cantonese
我记得我在哪里读到过，炒杂碎实际上可能是一道粤菜
dish that came from all of the leftovers and garbage in the kitchen.
来自厨房里所有的剩菜和垃圾。
You would just fry it together and it was a cheap, easy meal.
你只要把它们一起炒，就是一顿便宜又简单的饭。
So, chopped suey.
所以，炒杂碎。
It's kind of like an English, it's like a pigeon English.
这有点像英语，像洋泾浜英语。
And well, this dish is basically that, right?
嗯，这道菜基本上就是那样，对吧？
It's just a lot of meat chunks mixed with some vegetables and you have some chopped
就是很多肉块混着一些蔬菜，然后你就有了炒
suey.
杂碎。
Exactly.
没错。
And there's also this other thing that's very common.
还有另一件很常见的东西。
People think about fortune cookies.
人们会想到幸运饼干。
You think of Chinese restaurants and Chinese food, you think of fortune cookies.
你想到中餐馆和中餐，就会想到幸运饼干。
That's right, but they don't have fortune cookies in China.
没错，但中国没有幸运饼干。
No, they don't.
不，没有。
One of my biggest disappointments.
这是我最大的失望之一。
So fortune cookie is a small cookie with a message inside.
所以幸运饼干是一种里面夹着纸条的小饼干。
So you have a piece of paper.
你有一张纸。
Be careful when you're eating these.
吃的时候要小心。
You don't want to eat the paper.
你不想把纸也吃掉。
But the paper sometimes says very strange things like, you will have a terrific number
但纸条上有时会说些很奇怪的话，比如“你将有一个极好的数字
seven.
七”。
Right, or something like that.
对，或者类似的东西。
So that's why they're fortune cookies.
所以这就是为什么它们叫幸运饼干。
They usually talk about your future or what's going to happen.
它们通常谈论你的未来或将要发生的事情。
Beware of whales.
小心鲸鱼。
But that's also an American invention that doesn't exist in China.
但这也是美国发明，中国没有。
It doesn't really come from China, right?
它并不是真正来自中国，对吧？
Exactly.
没错。
So if you have any other information about food, we're always glad to hear it.
所以如果你有其他关于食物的信息，我们总是很高兴听到。
Because we're always hungry.
因为我们总是很饿。
Or if you have a favorite Chinese food, please let us know.
或者如果你有最喜欢的中国菜，请告诉我们。
Our website is EnglishPod.com.
我们的网站是 EnglishPod.com。
We can't wait to hear from you and we will talk to you next time.
我们迫不及待想听到你的消息，下次再聊。
All right, bye.
好的，再见。
Woo hoo!
呜呼！